hey everybody it is Jack Murphy here
from Jack Murphy live.com welcome to the
first episode of the Jack Murphy live
podcasts after many many requests
I have finally pulled the trigger and we
are doing this for real the goal of this
podcast is to bring you guys experts in
a cross-section of fields to help us all
better understand the world around us
personally I love in-depth conversations
with interesting intelligent people and
I'd love to hear what they have to say
when given more than just a two-minute
segment on-air on this podcast we're
gonna cover a wide range of topics like
politics culture sex and relationships
the media and more we're gonna have a
couple of rotating regulars like my good
friend wil chamberlain who is a legal
expert and a political commentary common
commentator as well as my lovely
girlfriend the redhead
to give us a female's perspective at
times be prepared the subject material
is going to bounce around a lot and
cover a lot of different ground and some
of it is definitely adult only not for
vulgarity or anything like that but
because of adult themes like sex and
relationships like I said people have
been asking me to do this for a long
time and I'm excited to get started I
think one of the best skills and my
skill stack is asking people probing
questions and guiding them along
interesting threads and then tying it
all together and relating it to the big
picture the guest list that we have
coming up is exciting and it is totally
blowing my mind there are multiple PhDs
lined up high profile experts in their
fields high-ranking government officials
as well as well-known journalists and
established independent media types the
content is going to be a little edgy but
it will be very informative and always
super interesting my first guest is
certainly all of those things his name
is Jeffrey Miller and he is an
evolutionary psychologist with an
undergraduate degree from Columbia
University and a PhD from Stanford and
cognitive psychology he is currently a
tenured professor at the University of
New Mexico Jeffrey has written over a
hundred academic papers countless
articles and he's published four books
including the mating mind and a book
called mate or what women wants he has
given lectures all over the world
he's taught at New York University
London School of Economics and UCLA his
work has been featured in nature science
the New York Times Washington Post The
Economist CNN NPR National Geographic
etc etc you get the picture
needless to say Jeffrey is a bonafide
expert in his field and a fascinating
guy to talk to but before we get to all
that I want to mention that this podcast
is brought to you by democrat to
deplorable why 9 million obama voters
ditched the democrats and embraced
donald trump this is a book that i wrote
myself and i published earlier this year
it's got a ton of original research it's
not just some guy ranting into the ether
i conducted a national survey with over
1500 respondents 267 questions so I have
a treasure trove of original original
research and data I interviewed people
over Skype from all over the country and
I even got in my car and just drove
around trying to talk to the real people
who once voted for Barack Obama but then
decided to ditch the Democrats and
embrace Donald Trump there's nine
million people there's nine million
people that did that and in an election
in 2016 which was decided by 77,000
votes over three states there's no
question that the Democrats are
deplorable voting bloc is one most vote
powerful voting blocs in America my book
takes a very deep dive into the cultural
political economic and all kinds of
reasons that created the environment in
which these people who proudly voted for
Barack Obama also proudly voted for
Donald Trump this book is not Trump you
know is the greatest thing in the whole
world kind of thing I'm not a trump
sycophant by any means and it's not
necessarily a book just straight bashing
Hillary Clinton in fact the tone of the
book is disarming it's interesting it's
engaging and it's really a stories of
the people who had their transfer
transformation and their transformative
experience which brought them to ditch
the Dems and embrace Donald Trump so go
out there get a copy you can find it on
amazon.com also please when you're done
reading leave a review if you know good
bad or the ugly the more reviews that I
get the more Amazon is likely to start
promoting it to the rest of the people
on their website and that's
way to get the message out you can also
find out more from me by following me on
twitter at jerk at Jack Murphy live go
to my website and check out all the
essays there's like 75 essays there from
the last three years at Jack Murphy
live.com while you're there sign up for
my email list and get exclusive
members-only content as well as pre
release and early release essays before
they're launched and sent out to the
public at large but now it's time for us
to get to our first guest
Jeffrey Miller I interviewed him while I
was in New Mexico this week I was
scheduled to speak at the University of
New Mexico law school as part of my
Democrat - the plural 20:18 fault war
but as my bags were packed and I was
just getting ready to go to bed for my
early flight the next day I found out
that the faculty member at the law
school had sponsored me who had paid for
my flight and paid for my hotel and
arranged the talk and promoted it she
had just been told that the talk had to
be canceled the head of the law school
called her and along with security and
they told her that they had received
threats that they were worried about the
security and they thought that it was
too dangerous to have a political
discussion so close to the midterm
elections this was the day before the
midterms and so they banned me and D
platform me because of what is in
Democrats are deplorable and the message
that I'm trying to bring I'm out here
building bridges and people were trying
to tear me down so that should give you
a good idea the climate that were
operating in but being the guy that I am
after they canceled me I still decided
to go okay my flights paid for the
hotels played for plus I had two very
interesting and important interviews set
up and one of them was with Jeffrey
Miller and so while I was out there
Jeffrey was kind enough to bring me into
his home we sat down at his dining room
table and after we got to know each
other a little bit we let the tape go
and started talking
what follows is about an hour and 45
minutes of an in-depth conversation that
spans a multitude of topics including
evolutionary psychology mating mating
patterns among humans relationships new
kinds of relations
chips politics culture feminism
masculinity femininity and all how all
these things are tied together and we
talk about the factors that influence
things from a macro level all the way to
the Supreme Court in the presidency of
the United States all the way down to
our relationships and down to the
dining-room table and so without further
ado I present to you the first episode
of Jack Murphy live podcast with Jeffrey
Miller thank you for listening hey
Jeffrey hey how you doing I'm doing
really good thanks for having me here
murder we are here at Jeffrey's home in
Albuquerque and he's been so gracious to
invite me to the to the dining room
table just sit down have a talk we had
connected over Twitter some time ago and
I've been you know we've been
communicating about various issues and
one thing that we we had a little
discussion over that I want to get to
eventually here was Jordan Peterson had
a brouhaha and the press when he was
talking about his notion of enforced
monogamy yeah and I brought that up
thinking that it was very interesting
how Jordan Peterson was able to trigger
people into sort of advocating for the
breakdown of the traditional family as a
way to just argue with Jordan Peterson
and you said that you wanted to have a
talk about that and I thought that was
great and I would definitely like to get
to that but the first thing I wanted to
talk about is just sort of lead in was
we were talking earlier about your
experience in writing a book with Tucker
Max and I was hoping you could share
sort of how you came to work with him
and what that experience was like and
sort of some of your takeaways you know
from that I think Tucker had read my
spent book and really enjoyed it it was
about consumerism and business and how
people sort of signal their traits
through the goods and services that they
buy and display and I happen to be in a
social psych conference in Austin Texas
where Tucker lives a few years ago and
we happen to get together for dinner and
we talked about kind of the the
difficulties that young men face and
dating and the
they have about evolution and women hand
and mate choice and kind of what vector
to go and what direction to try to
develop men and so Tucker and I decided
we should write a book together and that
ended up being the mate book made and
hardback or what women want and
paperback and we tried to integrate the
evolutionary psychology that that I know
and that he actually read quite a bit
about with his sort of real-life
experience of interacting with a lot of
women and being in the scene the dating
scene for a while we learned a lot from
doing our podcast the mating grounds
where young men would call in with their
issues and we would kind of give them
advice but we're what were some of the
main issues he said that he identified
that the young men were having problems
today and you know I think right now the
the popularity of Jordan Peterson
filling up you know arena not arenas but
you know large halls all across the
world actually now is like thousands of
people you know it's speaking to the
fact that there's sort of a Lost Boys
generation out there so what what did
you and Tucker identify as being some of
the problems I think the number one
thing was that a lot of young men don't
really have the perspective-taking
ability they can't really put themselves
in the heads or the shoes of women and
ask well what's it like to be a woman
what's their perspective what did they
really want and how can I sort of
deliver it to them how can I make myself
into the kind of guy who's actually
attractive and compelling to women and
you know we know from psychology that
men are not as good at that kind of
perspective taking or mind-reading as
women are so when men go into the dating
scene and you know high school or
college they really don't have a lot of
good advice from the culture or their
parents about what is happening
realistically between the sexes but
they're getting some advice somewhere
they're getting a lot of sort of
misleading advice that tends to be
either sort of very politically correct
that pretends there's no sex differences
or they're they're reading you know
pickup artists
kind of red pill stuff which has a lot
of Merit to
but but make some key mistakes you know
in my humble opinion so what we wanted
to do is kind of well we'll get back to
that yeah yeah I hope so
we we tried to offer a kind of
perspective that's based on science but
also based on you know the lived
experience that the Tucker and I had in
our own relationships and what what did
you guys sort of identify as an attitude
or a perspective that young men were
getting from culture and society that
was inaccurate or even misleading or
even in detrimental I think there was a
lot of misunderstanding about power
dynamics in relationships where a lot of
guys thought okay either I have to be
mr. nice and super agreeable and
basically beg for sex and you know kind
of feminist Ally and try to insinuate
myself into a woman's affections through
a kind of almost political manipulation
or I have to go to the opposite extreme
I have to make myself into a kind of
psychopathic alpha male who doesn't have
any empathy or consideration for women
or any degree of agreeableness and there
again we tried to make a sort of middle
path that says women are very attracted
to power and dominance and status and
prestige and confidence that is true but
women also want to see the qualities and
a man that would make for a long a long
term partner a good partner a good dad
and a lot of that depends on you know
agreeableness and kindness and and
understanding the woman's point of view
and your future children's points of
view right Psychopaths don't make good
dads and and that's the argument we made
that men have to become what we call
tender defenders they have to be capable
of defending women and kids and women
have to trust
it's true but they also have to be
tender most of the time I think you know
some people that I know would say that
that's building a better betta have you
ever heard that phrase before yeah and I
understand that perspective but I think
the whole alpha-beta terminology is very
misleading I think that those are great
concepts if you're describing gorillas
where there really is a sort of
alpha-beta hierarchy likewise with
orangutans but humans lived in you know
social tribal groups a very long time we
have multiple sources of status not just
one we don't just rely on physical
dominance we rely on intelligence
creativity reputation how much value we
can add to the group what our moral
virtues are etc and that's how humans
typically get status and what makes us
attractive to each other so any given
group yeah maybe there's one leader but
not everybody can be a leader not all
guys can sort of be the so-called Alpha
nor should they try to be nor is that
necessarily the morally best thing to be
nor nor a society that are off if you
know all the guys are trying to compete
to be the Alpha right I think you can
certainly have a levelling up of
confidence I think that's the key thing
of young men figure out how do I build
skills that give me a legitimate
confidence and a sense of self-worth
that's great but don't confuse that with
trying to be the top dog
I remember when Jordan Peterson broke
onto the scene he used the phrase
dominance hierarchies quite a bit and I
think over time he started to actually
swap that phrase out for I believe
competence hierarchies now is that what
you're sort of getting at soar the
difference there because I think it's
pretty clear that we exist in a
hierarchy and I'm curious to understand
your perspective on the
does that hierarchy start in aggregate
and work its way all the way down to the
family level and within our familiar
relationships with our spouses with our
children in our community sort of how if
you can speak to that dominance vs.
competence is it the same thing is it
different and where and where and when
and how do they start or stop yeah I
think Jack this is a really good
question and it's very confusing to a
lot of people so on the one hand you
have a social status hierarchy which is
within a group who is recognized as
having the highest status second-highest
etc and people typically agree on this
there is a consensus like this person is
more of a leader this person is more of
a quiet follower but separately from
that there's a spectrum of competence or
capability and the main thing Tucker and
I argued in the mate book is
fundamentally women are attracted to
competence even if it doesn't show up at
the moment in the state of hierarchy so
if a guy is really good at doing all
kinds of things
hunting fighting taking care of his
friends socializing building his
reputation displaying signs of
confidence and capability that is
extremely attractive to most women most
of the time and you can do that even if
you're not in a kind of leadership
position right you can even do that if
you're a high school sophomore or of
course you're not you're not the top dog
because there are juniors and seniors
kind of above you and that's what we try
to encourage the young men to do is kind
of don't worry about your status or your
dominance first build your confidence
get good at lots of things mm-hmm and
this these hierarchies do they do they
find them their way into our family
structures as well or are those more
Galit Arian or how does that work well I
think in any given relationship you know
there's a power dynamic where typically
one person has or ends up with a little
bit more power than the other person a
lot of that has to do with relative mate
value right whoever has a little bit
higher made value overall
whoever has more options has more
bargaining power in a relationship if it
would be easier for them to leave have
more bargaining power they tend to be
more dominant well do you find in your
research and in your time with the
podcast and talking to people that women
will willingly enter into a relationship
in which they have higher status or a
higher sort of mate value relative to
their male partner and if they do is it
satisfying you do see that but I think
typically the happiest most stable most
successful relationships have two
qualities one there's kind of a division
of labour with regard to competence so
that the woman might be stronger and
better at certain things the guy
stronger and better other things and
they complement each other and they're a
good match in that regard so the guy
might think oh man she's kind of
dominant to me with regard to certain
issues but I'm dominant to her with
regard to other domains of life or other
issues my dad's favorite joke for
example is well in happy marriage the
woman makes you know two really trivial
decisions like where they live who they
socialize with where they send their
kids to school the translation of the
oldest is you know how to spend their
money
what house to buy and the math makes the
important decisions like really how we
should relate to China and and you know
what about brexit and so forth and I
think there's a grain of truth in that
that often women have a lot of kind of
hidden private power over money and
parenting and how the relationship goes
and a couple social life and the man
thinks he's sort of dominant because
maybe he's got stronger political
opinions or maybe makes the money you
know but the woman spends more of it
stuff like that mm-hmm
so it's in this case it's a sort of
Mirage yeah I think it's a mirage and I
think smart women throughout history
have always known that they have quite a
bit more power than their husbands think
they have
I heard of I heard a phrase once I said
the hand that rocks the cradle rules the
world yeah and of course women also have
a lot of power to shape the abilities
and and ethics of the next generation
you know as mom's and as people who kind
of set the moral tone for society anyway
I saw a Pew study that showed that
women's may preferences are for men with
higher education level and perhaps a
higher earning income potential in in
the United States now where women
outnumber men on college campuses I
think it's three to two and growing and
fewer and fewer men are getting college
education more more women are getting
college education as I've seen studies
that show that in a hundred and forty
eight out of 150 metropolitan areas in
the United States women recent graduates
are out earning their male counterparts
how do you see that playing out in terms
of mate choice mate selection and
happiness within relationships at cetera
I think it can be very tough if people
don't kind of update their make
preferences so there's a tradition in
America of women not wanting to marry
somebody who makes less than them right
no is that a tradition or is that
something that has evolved over time as
a way to survive and to evolve you know
into the best that they can be I think
in a way it is a tradition but it's a
deep tradition I think it goes back to
kind of the invention of agriculture you
know ten thousand years ago I think ever
since then women who have been in groups
that did city-states and agriculture and
inherited land and wealth have been
under a lot of pressure and I mean
literal evolutionary selection pressure
to do the hypergamy thing to find guys
who have land and wealth and an expected
future stream of wealth and the women
who didn't care about that and those
groups kind of died out so we're left
with women who are concerned about is
10,000 years enough time
to make such a change or a dent in our
sort of aggregate expression of our
genes and preferences sure why not I
mean look at how quickly hundreds of
different dog breeds diverged from just
a few different subspecies of wolves and
last I mean most of those breeds are
only a few hundred years so it doesn't
isn't that like I can touch a controlled
environment where like humans are
dictating that evolution that I mean
sort of left to the genetic marketplace
is ten thousand years really enough time
to make such a profound change and I
guess the question I'm asking is does
this preference go back further than ten
thousand years yeah if you study you
know hunter-gatherer tribal societies
who certainly also see this tendency
towards hypergamy where the women will
pay a bit of attention to who's got
dominant status prestige who's a good
hunter if you're hanging around the
campfire at night which guy says things
that everybody else listens to versus
which guys don't say anything or you
know say dumb stuff that everybody
ignores they pay a lot of attention to
that of course but I think the focus on
wealth is perhaps relatively new and I
think we should distinguish between like
hunting ability is one thing but making
you know a professional living in a
complex market economy is a different
thing right so it seems it seems to me
that female reaction to a successful
expression of like physicality is is
maybe in a instinctual response whereas
reaction to your wealth and income may
be calculated well I think they're both
instinctual responses one just goes back
further than the other mmm-hmm I think
you know females of almost all species
that we've studied generally have a
tendency to prefer to mate with males
that are physically larger stronger
healthier more energetic more capable
than their female counterpart or them
that other matters than other males
right yeah so what happens to this
mating process the sorting process when
you have fewer and fewer men you know
attaining you know higher levels of
education and income and then you
combine it with a popular culture that
seems to be denigrating masculinity and
male performance what is that going to
do to the innate wiring of 22 year old
woman today who is trying to find her
place in the mating market but you know
maybe there's a contradiction from what
she's seeing culturally than what she's
feeling on the inside but yeah it's a
great question if I was a 22 year old
woman in in modern society I imagine I
would be really really frustrated
because I would have these kind of
instinctual attractions to certain male
traits that are in relatively short
supply partly due the you know
technology and the economy and the
culture and so forth but I would also be
kind of feeling guilty about having
those preferences where does that come
from I think it's from a kind of
politically correct ideology and gender
feminism that says you should be going
for men who aren't necessarily
physically strong and capable but are
just nice and allies that you should go
for men who have the right ethical
values rather than necessarily the best
future earners or the ones who are
socially a professionally competent and
and so men aren't living up to women's
standards but also I think women aren't
being very articulate about what they're
really wanting really when when you say
that the first thing I think of a Sheryl
Sandberg and her book where she says
they you know you should date all the
bad boys and have fun with them until
you're ready to settle down and then
find yourself a good little earner I
mean that to me seems to be pretty darn
explicit I think that's not the worst
advice I've heard but for the guy I mean
that so this is I think this is
something that people are really feeling
right now which is there's a difference
for between being desired by your mate
for urinate physicality or your
sexuality
or you're just you know brutishness as
it were versus being perceived as a
valuable business partner and then
valuable for your sort of economic or
contribution to the relationship and I
think that the former makes people feel
like you know with increased vitality it
makes them feel excited it makes them
feel awesome but to be the guy who gets
married you know to the woman in her 30s
then who is now the one who's gonna be
like oh the good dad or the good earner
could provide her good partner I think
that makes guys feel kind of used yeah
alters that I mean men are status
objects and women are sex objects and
neither of us like to be treated as
objects in that kind of way and that's
what a transactional way but I think the
thing is that you know there's a
difference between and what guys get
very confused about this like you're big
strong guy and and some guys are kind of
born that way though that's their
genetics but whatever you're your genes
are it's like not that hard to stay in
pretty good shape if you work at it a
bit and you don't have to be you know
the strongest MMA fighter on campus to
be attractive to women I think women are
often just looking for a certain basic
minimum level of literal physical
fitness I'm like if you're fit enough to
walk around and do stuff and have
vigorous sex and you know be active in
multiple ways that's good enough but a
lot of guys aren't making aren't
reaching that standard no definitely not
and I think that what we've seen is that
the importance for you know keeping
yourself in good shape and for just
general basic fitness and you know with
the obesity and all the unhealthy
behaviors that we've accepted in our
culture today that I think is also
feeding into this general
dissatisfaction everybody's having in
the in the mating market maybe I'm
making a broad generalization when I'm
saying like general dissatisfaction but
I think your experience with the power
passed in the book with Jordan Peterson
is saying what I've seen in my own
writing what guys I've talked to be they
red pill writers or just general you
know masculinity you know writers that
everybody is sort of getting the same
sense out there that there's a you know
disenchantment people are disappointed
things aren't working the way that
they're supposed to work and I think
it's because we're giving people the
wrong messages and we're also building a
society in which women are sort of
building themselves up into a situation
which other men are just gonna just fail
them if they're just not gonna generate
that innate sexual desire and and I you
know I keep coming back to that because
for me personally I I was in a marriage
that was that was just crashed and
burned and I had fallen apart I were
gotten fat and I was out of shape and I
was drinking too much and I wasn't doing
anything that would generate desire from
my from my ex-wife and once I got
divorced I realized I wasn't doing
anything that was going to generate
desire in anybody right so I figured out
through trial and error that I had to
like get my ass in shape and I had to
work out and I had to become physically
fit and physically dominant and carry
myself in a way that that exude that if
irrespective of whatever my intellectual
capabilities were my professional
capabilities and that was a difficult
lesson to learn because I think maybe
there's a sense of entitlement out there
with with guys and you know they haven't
put it together yet that it's sort of
like all on them and you know that's
that's my main message that I'm bringing
to guys which is that it's all on you
and that you you have the capability to
make make a change in your life that's
going to manifest itself and better
healthier more satisfying relationships
with both your significant others and
just your friends and people around you
and where is that message today and I
mean the weird thing is I agree with
everything you just said um people think
of this as kind of a marginal issue
compared to like oh the the election or
whatever but actually a civilization
that doesn't offer a viable mating
market and that doesn't offer norms and
standards and
you know habits and institutions that
allow young men to meet young women and
get together and have relationships and
have babies and have families that's a
failed civilization right and and not
just get together and have babies but
have long lasting satisfying
relationships because it seems it seems
to be a phenomenon where people can get
together in the chemical lusts
passionate period of love and and have a
baby but then like two or three years
later they realize you know like our
triggers aren't being hit here and
nobody's happy and there's a lot of a
lot of divorce like around around that
time I don't have any hard statistics on
it but anecdotally I have seen it I've
experienced it myself it's interesting
you know you you're absolutely right
about a society that fails to to sort of
clear the mating market is a doomed
Society in the long run and I first my
book Democrats a deplorable it's about
politics and culture but I started
writing about relationship issues just
like this you know and through my own
personal experience I mean everything
that I've written about has been through
my own personal experience trial and
error a first-person narrative and like
really trying to share you know what's
happened to me in the past and and put
that out there for people in a raw and
honest way and in doing that I realized
that the issues that were affecting our
our dating and mating markets and
disrupting the bedroom are also
disrupting the the nation and disrupting
our politics and our culture or vice
versa or whatever but they're all
they're all related and intertwined and
you know gonna shift subject here just a
little bit but it came down to sort of
this radical feminism and modern
feminism today and sort of this desire
to wipe out the differences between men
and women both on a obvious physical
level on a performative level in
professions and jobs and this demand
that everybody and everything be
completely equal and then if you suggest
otherwise your rates as bigoted
homophobia sexist misogynist and whatnot
and when I saw the cabin all
confirmation hearings
the Supreme Court recently and I heard
the Senate Judiciary Committee people
the Senators up there using the language
of radical feminism and using these
concepts and ideologies about believe
all women because all sexes can be rape
and rape is about power and we must
believe all survivors and you know these
things you can you know a real feminist
scholar could track tracked out all the
way back into the feminist literature
but to see it burst forth onto the
biggest national platform that there is
you know this court Supreme Court
hearings and the presidents involved and
it really hammered home to me that all
these things that I've been discovering
through trial and error were not insane
right and I'm not crazy
and this stuff is real and it's really
happening and it's really putting you
know it's really divisive and it's
really you know I think if we don't do
something about it it's gonna have some
long-term damaging consequences do you
you know what do you think about that
yeah we're at a peak of of mistrust
between the sexes and I think it's
completely that's the real toxicity it's
not toxic masculinity it's toxic
mistrust and I think it's it's fed by
kind of media and academic culture that
exaggerated Samara cos problems
extremely like the rate of you know rape
in America's fallen by at least half or
maybe three times compared to the early
90s oh yeah I mean the chart is just a
steady downward joke there's a doubt as
far back as you can look and and the
overall level like in the u.s. compared
to like India has a real great problem
India is very sexist patriarchal porn is
outlawed you know young men are sexually
frustrated there's not a culture of sort
of casual sex etc so they have a huge
problem of sexual coercion there is a
big problem of sexual coercion in
America but it's gradually kind of
fading away for various reasons but the
more overblown it is by the media the
harder it is for young people to go on
dates and
but is it just the media that's over
blowing it I mean I went to I went to
the the protests out in front of the
Supreme Court and there was a woman up
there so she was an executive director
of rape ed on campus and she said one in
three women on campus will be victims of
sexual violence this year now I
understand that they have taken the the
surveys and the the questions they've
expanded what it means to be a victim of
sexual assault and it's really a you
know down now even if you looked at the
wrong way but I'm exaggerating here but
basically they expanded the definition
and you know these studies used the big
scare number was one in five and that
was one in four and now it's one in
three
so it's the is the read of sexual
violence on college campus has it really
gone up that much to one in three I mean
if this was a real number would you or
any other father in America send your
daughter to a college campus and so this
hysteria is not just from the media it's
from these are nonprofits these are
people well yeah answer advocacy groups
these advocacy groups nonprofits that
often have a vested interest in
overblowing these statistics but this I
mean this is generally true for
nonprofits right like World Wildlife
Fund will exaggerate the rate of
extinction and Greenpeace will
exaggerate the rate of global warming I
mean of course everybody who has a sort
of vested interest and a problem wants
to make the problem seem really big but
the best statistics show you know rates
of sexual coercion are dropping on
campuses and it's much safer for a young
woman to be on a campus or not to be on
a campus and that message is getting
lost and also I think that there's such
an expanded definition of what kinds of
relationships between men and women are
problematic like for example the idea
that if you're tipsy
you can't give any consent a lot of the
one-in-three stats are basically women
who hook up when they're tipsy because
it's considered to be sexually
course--it if there
you know tipsy um and what I found
interesting about those studies is that
at the end they ask oh did you report
this and they don't do people those self
reporters on these tests and these
quizzes say they don't report them and
why didn't they report them because they
didn't feel like it was sexual violence
but then the people who are doing my
study the researchers say oh it was
sexual yes right exactly and that I've
asked my own University like okay what
exactly is our policy let's say a two
gay guys two gay students get together
and they both tipsy and they have sex
who raped who or did they both rape each
other or was it not rape the coordinator
or our policies and there is no answer
for that right and that seems like it
seems like we must be living in some
sort of bizarre world where that
actually becomes a valid question but it
is a valid question and in the context
of seeing the Supreme Court hearing
dominated by these ideas it's no longer
just a fringe thing to think about I
don't think I say I think that this is
now in the mainstream it's affecting our
government it's affecting our culture
it's affecting us and on aggregate and
it's gonna affect our mating and mating
sorting and our genetic development so
this to me is you know it's I don't
think it's an existential problem but
you know maybe it's approaching that I
mean this is something that I think
needs a lot more attention and a
solution what what do you think we do
about this well you know look if if
you're talking about let's say
government policy at economic level the
first thing to ask from like my
libertarian perspective is what could be
the unanticipated consequences or the
side effects of the policy or how will
people respond to the new incentives in
ways he might not have predicted and
that might be counterproductive people
don't tend to do that when they get in
the sexual realm of talking about well
we should adopt these sexual norms and
values they don't typically ask okay if
we do that what are the unanticipated
side effects like if you have new
policies on campus that basically
disincentivize students from dating
other students
well okay they'll date non students or
they won't date at all and maybe become
frustrated and depressed so what are
those costs nobody seems to be
skank those kinds of questions um but I
see it like when I teach my human
sexuality class I'll sometimes ask the
students how how do you guys feel all
about dating somebody else on campus and
a lot of the guys will say I wouldn't
dare it is too risky why the hell would
I - the risk of somebody misinterpreting
something or or having regrets about a
date or a sexual experience and and so
they're they're basically deterred from
forming relationships and when I went to
college in the 80s there's like we had
relationship problems but we didn't
worry about the university kind of being
like this draconian rule enforcer no cuz
they just spent the 60s and 70s kicking
the universities out of the dormitory
bedrooms right yeah they said we don't
want in loco parentis we don't want the
universities to take the place of you
know parents and our dating lives we
want sexual freedom right now we've
basically lost all that well I see this
as a major issue facing us culturally
and politically and in my research and
my experiences I've seen I would tie
this back although back to title nine
regulations and back to the Obama era
changes to the sexual harassment
policies and procedures and the way that
it was Joe Biden in particular who got
you know sort of convinced by some
radical feminists that this was one in
fun what's fun in five then that the one
in five number was really real and this
was a rape epidemic right this was a
national crisis that needed to be
handled and so from Washington and I'm
working in education too so I'm very
familiar with the way that's a federal
policy education policy tied to money
can manifest itself in our in our
society and our relationships and change
human behavior and so the way I see it
is that there's like this web reaching
out from Washington DC that was
politically motivated that then changed
the incentive structure for universities
across camp across the country who under
the threat of losing their money have
now expanded you know if not not just
from like preventing women from being
harassed to the point that they can't
get their education
but now they have to actually stamp out
any sense of harassment sort of before
it happens I think something like 250
colleges across the country of these
things called bias response teams where
year you know students are instructed to
rat on each other
somebody says anything that's that's
offensive you know and these things
sound absolutely insane if you're just
sort of sticking your toe into this
conversation for the first time but
these are facts I mean this is real
stuff and so to me I see it as being all
politically related and I think that we
have like sort of a new crisis on our
hands in in instead of the fake crisis
then again it comes from the Democratic
policies and the sort of infiltration of
radical feminism into the Democratic
Party and so to me it looks like a major
national issue the fact that there's
kids in your classes that say that they
won't date each other on campus so how
how do you how do i how do we how do my
listeners how do my readers what do we
do about this like how do we make these
changes cuz I'll be honest I was
practically a single-issue voter with
Donald Trump when he when he you know
alluded to making title nine reforms and
my just big hopes that he was gonna you
know that to me was such a high leverage
issue that you know that sort of sealed
it for me so what's your take on that
hmm I think it is important for
listeners to understand that virtually
all of the ideological pressure on
campuses comes from the left not from
the right if it came from the right I
would not have been able to teach a
class on polyamory and open sexuality I
would be terrified of what I teach in my
regular human sexuality class in terms
of potential conservative blowback
because I cover a lot of kind of edgy
topics you know I cover the history of
gay rights I cover kink and BDSM I cover
hypergamy I cover a lot of that stuff
that many American conservatives
particularly you know Christian
conservatives would find like then maybe
they don't want their kids to hear about
that stuff
but they have no voice nobody in higher
education administration is listening to
Christian conservatives about what their
complaints are they are listening to the
left
darrel listening to gender feminists so
this isn't just an issue of you know
dating on campus it's also an issue of
what our professor is allowed to teach
because remember title 9 originally was
about equal access basically to college
athletics now it's turned into extremely
strong constraints on free speech
because a lot of policy a lot of
universities have policies now that say
if you say anything that any student
considers to be sexist or stereotyping
they can report it to administrators and
then you as a faculty member can be
censured and you know punished because
he or whatever saying something sexist
okay how do you define that it could
potentially be any scientific claim
about sex differences
well the James d'amore Google memo issue
came up and you know I'm just going to
assume basic understanding from our
audience on what happened there but the
national labor review board when they
went over the complaint there in their
response they said that any discussion
of sexual differences in personality
aptitude capabilities was considered
harassment yeah and that's where we're
at as America and it's insane because
the amount of scientific evidence for
those differences is very strong you
know it's at least as strong as the
evidence for let's say a global warming
but one of those issues there's you know
there's a line that we're supposed to
follow that Mithen point right well
which makes me laugh because the folks
on the left will say that the people on
the right are science deniers but when
it comes to gender and sexuality and
whatnot that it's definitely people on
the left that are the science deniers
here absolutely yeah the left tends to
often believe in kind of blank slate
views and basically deny the evolution
of human would you do you explain that
concept for people that are listening
please because I think this is really
crucial and also to like our political
coalition's I think that we're sorting
around this idea actually okay so the
blank slate is the view that evolution
may have shaped our bodies to have human
form but it didn't really have any
significant effect on our minds other
than just endow us with a general
purpose learning capacity that means we
can soak up ideas from culture and from
other people so if you're a blank slate
er then you believe that very few
psychological traits are heritable in
the sense that you know individuals will
resemble their parents for genetic
rather than just cultural reasons and
also you don't tend to believe that
there are significant evolved
differences between the sexes you tend
to believe there aren't sort of
heritable personality traits you tend
not to believe there's such a thing as
general intelligence that's heritable
and the difference between people and
the left has basically always been the
side of blank slate er is because they
want people to be naturally good and
perfectible preferably through state
intervention and they really don't want
to think about any innate differences
between people or between species or
between the sexes but this is clearly
contradicted by by a datum yeah and I
you know I think Steven Pinker's best
book it's called the blank slate and you
should read it if you believe in the
blank slate it will tear your mind a new
opening into reality no they'll just set
it on fire so burn it it's heresy but
what's amazing about that book is it was
written I think in 2002 and when you
read it today
it seems like because I read it again
just like a year ago and see it reads
like case closed
yeah right like blank blank slate is it
no does not exist period end of story
next discussion but in the preface to
the latest edition and he's like I can't
believe we're still having this debate
and I can't believe that this is still
an issue and I would argue that it's
even more pronounced than it was 15 15
years ago yeah absolutely
it's surest and the crazy thing about it
is if you actually care about other
people and a society where everyone is
cared for it's really helpful to
acknowledge that there are heritable
individual differences in intelligence
and conscientiousness meaning willpower
and lots of traits so not everybody is
gonna be able to become an Elon Musk in
fact not everybody maybe is capable of
finishing college and learning through
college textbooks and lectures and
that's okay but instead the left has
adopted this delusional fantasy that
says if you just shove enough education
down people's throats everyone can be
competitive in a global you know
information and technology based economy
and that leads to disillusionment
disappointment frustration shame you
know victim blaming and it actually
leads to a nation where everybody who is
successful looks down with total
contempt on everybody who isn't
successful and you see that with the
elite attitudes towards let's say Trump
voters right well you know what's so I'm
six foot four so I've been blessed
genetically with height but I played
basketball in high school and I'm not
blessed genetically enough with height
or athleticism to become like a college
basketball player or a professional
basketball player and I guarantee you
that professional basketball player does
not look at me with contempt because I'm
incapable of playing professional
basketball based on my genetics and I'm
also not the most dominant guy in every
room I mean all the time but not all
I'm not the smartest guy I haven't been
the leader in every situation that I've
been in and you know what I'm okay with
that
maybe it's because I do have a
relatively high put you know status in
my you know circles and whatnot but I
think that there is a certain assumption
that people are incapable of
acknowledging their place in the
hierarchy and would feel somehow I don't
know angry hateful something else
horribly negative if you know when they
you know understand that their place you
know where where it is and I think that
this blank slate stuff is a way to as
you said you know find a perfect ability
in the human condition and human
performance but then it leads exactly to
what you're saying which is well if you
didn't succeed then you just didn't try
hard enough
yeah exactly I mean to me you know the a
fundamental question for civilizations
that have you know a population with a
distribution of traits is not what's the
upper limit of success if if you have
extraordinary abilities rather it's does
your society give people with an IQ of a
hundred and an average degree of
willpower a reasonable shot at finding a
mate and having a family and doing
meaningful work and having self-respect
and if a society can't offer that to
literally average people if it kind of
sweeps that issue under the rug that
that's a failed society mmm-hmm and I
think that's something the left is not
willing to engage with mm-hmm you know
you can't solve that problem by just
expanding the welfare state or teaching
everybody gender feminism or you know
calling everybody racist that's those
aren't the viable solutions well then
there's other things that come out of
this blank slate notion which is that
gender you know is is a social construct
that's not innate to your biology and
that our hormones for example don't have
anything to do with the way that we
behave now I'm a I myself I'm on hormone
replacement therapy
my testosterone levels checked when
about eight years ago maybe and it was
about 300 and that's really low for a
guy my age at the time and I got I got
back I got on a sascha replacement
therapy and it elevated my mood reduce
my anxiety it gave me a little bit more
confidence and it made me feel much
better people will seek out hormone
therapy for its enhancement on mood and
performance as much as they do on for
physical capabilities and then when we
see people that want to transition from
women to men you know the first thing
that they do is they take hormones and
so I see this happening and I see this
in the transgender issue I see this sort
of prescription of how to honey change
your gender you start taking male
hormones you know you're injecting
biology into your and you have increased
levels of aggression you have increased
and this is self-reported from
transitioning women right that they have
increased levels of aggression and
increased levels of sexual sex drive
higher confidence etc but then it
doesn't square up with this idea that
gender is a social construct and so I
think that a lot of frustration that you
know people that read me and you know
people that I have followed our feeling
is that this blank slate thing is like I
think they really believe it but at the
same time it's also opportunistic and
then you know they can sort of toss it
out the window when they want to push a
political agenda and I'm finding you
know one of the sort of theories that I
put forth and in my book Democrat
deplorable is that our new political
coalition's are going to be forming
around whether or not you believe in
blank slate theory or whether you
believe in some element of biological
determinism or essentialism what do you
think about that how did you see that
manifesting itself in our political
environment I think that's already sort
of happening but in a way like let's say
both Republicans and Democrats and
neither of them are willing to
acknowledge heritable differences in
capabilities right and neither of them
really are willing to talk explicitly
about sex differences or to connect kind
of economic and social policies to
family policies
pronatalist issues or whatever i can
imagine a political landscape changing
where people do have much more open
debates about sort of blank slate versus
evolved in heritable traits but that
would be awkward for both parties
because it means you know if you're kind
of a free-market semi libertarian
republican and you acknowledge oh wait
but there are heritable differences and
intelligence and willpower and ambition
and mental health then how do we provide
a society that gives everybody a you
know reasonable shot I think I think
some some libertarian Republican would
just even Nix that question altogether
from the start how do we provide well
yeah I don't mean necessarily provide by
like redistributing wealth but I mean
it's sort of creating a set of social
norms and institutions and values at the
cultural level not necessarily the
government level that actually give
everybody a shot at you know mating
success meaningful work families the
other thing is if you take a blank slate
approach to gender differences or sex
differences the way that actually plays
out is it simply D legitimizes
masculinity it doesn't deal agenda mais
femininity it doesn't deal each itemise
women's interests what it tends to do is
is you know puts men and things like
couples therapy situations where men
will say these are my preferences these
are my values this is what I'm missing
in their relationship and therapist is
typically female will say that's just
toxic masculinity that's not legitimate
I don't respect those needs you need to
become more like a woman hmm you need to
communicate more you need to do less
stonewalling you need to abandon your
you know need to like have occasional
sexual domination of your your
girlfriend or whatever
by contrast women are almost never told
your preferences aren't legitimate you
change them your need to communicate all
the time about everything isn't
legitimate that's just socialist nobody
gets told that right or your your
emotional jealousy right or your
emotional jealousy is illegitimate you
need to man up and and you know not not
feel that right so the burden is
basically put on men to deny or mask on
today on the basis that it's allegedly
socially constructed but there's a total
double standard women are never really
asked to overcome their sort of teman
ization by culture right well I think
that we've hit on enough points to where
you know my argument that you know there
is a attack on on masculinity that's
sort of structural and endemic to you
know our society today it's at the
national level it's on the policy level
it's in our universities it's
infiltrated all of our social
relationships it's down to it's even
inside of our familiar relationships
between couples it's a major and
significant issue but there's still like
a lot of shame around talking about this
matter and in your experience tying this
back with with Tucker and talking about
red pill stuff and talking about
masculinity and positive masculinity you
know I'm curious to hear what your
prescription would be because you know I
have seen and I'm telling you this year
with the Cavanagh thing really just for
10 years I thought I was crazy okay I
thought I thought I was just kind of
being a baby kind of making this up
kind of exaggerating these issues taking
things out of contexts you know or
misleading data and whatnot but I have
finally I finally submitted to the data
which is ironic because I've been
writing about this stuff for a long time
but still there was a part of me that
felt imposter II or sort of fake about
it but this year even in the last couple
of months really hammered it home for me
and for me personally you know no we're
not passing any new laws and I'm not
even looking for the government to do
that I'm trying to find a way that men
on an individual basis
and then sort of collectively as men
what what are we supposed to do and how
do we move forward and how do we how do
we get past the shame element of
acknowledging this sort of attack and
war for lack of a better word or this
conflict and and really get back to sort
of a cultural embrace of a positive
masculinity for Evan for everyone's
benefit I think we have to be able to
articulate number one why did
masculinity evolve to have the structure
it does right if you don't understand
that human evolution was characterized
by a lot of group versus group warfare
and a lot of male versus male fighting
and homicide within groups and a lot of
jostling for status because women made
it with higher status guys if you don't
accept that you can't it's really hard
to accept yourself as a man right if men
are men because of women basically men
are men because of women and because of
you know past male versus male
competition right and this is this is
mate selection this is the power of mate
selection it's a power mate selection
but it's also the power of which males
win the competition for land and
resources and and meat and status and
prestige so you know we're here our
dad's our granddad's were the winners
right of those competitions the ones who
lost those competitions didn't didn't
typically pass on their genes and
they're not our ancestors so we have to
kind of embrace that and go for better
or worse that's our evolutionary history
and here we are now what do we do about
it
and I think second we have to be able to
articulate to women the upsides of men
embracing and nurturing their
masculinity in a way that is hot and
sexy and meaningful and makes for better
relationships look women read romance
novels where there are bad boys and
rogues pirate captains Vikings whatever
that's the fantasy right I want a high
status confident effective fit guy who
can fight and it's not the deckhand and
and do all that stuff not the deckhand
not the not the gamma viking boy child
whatever and we have Ragnar that's yeah
we have to be able to remind women you
can have that you can still have that
passion in that power dynamic that
hotness for real in your life in your
relationship if you know you just kind
of allow men to do that and help them
level up and and allow them to express
that without sort of judging it
negatively mm-hmm
in my personal relationships I have
through trial and error figured out that
that's what works best for me is my
expression of masculinity and leadership
and you know dominance but not in not in
the negative way that the gender
feminists will have you believe and for
me what it means is really just having a
mission my mission first and taking care
of myself and my health and my physical
well-being first and that's not in a
selfish way that's in a way to make me
more useful to society you know the the
model that I've adopted is to you know
take care of yourself first and then
your family in your community and then
maybe if you can get that far you can
maybe help your near nation and the rest
of mankind but it all starts with you
taking care of yourself first and that
if that means missing out on you know
some family function because you liked
you need to go to the gym to get your
mind right and get your body right well
that's something that you have to do so
that you can be present and you can be
capable and you can be harder to kill
and you can be a more useful contributor
to your family and I think that somehow
that message that physic physicality and
this is something I've emphasized so all
my guys was like you know how do i how
do I just change my life how do I get
better relationships how do I do better
it's good at work how do I make more
money you know that's the first thing
you do is you take your ass down the gym
and you start squatting
and I think that that sort of
physicality culture gets get the mocks
and it's there's a shame shame factor
you know a man they use shame a lot
don't they and I guess what I'm thinking
of right now is if we are evolving
constantly evolving and I ideally were
or theoretically where we're moving
forward in a way that's sort of like a
you know the best of the fittest way for
us
aren't these ideology is this radical
feminism the shaming this anti
masculinity is there like anti Fitness
this is I don't know what the right word
is but you know it's just like a failed
evolutionary tactic is this something
that needs to die is it dis genic as we
said this just like there's a kind of
favor bound on the side jeans over good
jeans I mean it's hard to say cuz on the
one hand part of me is like this is
terrible it's selecting the wrong genes
the gene pool is gonna go to hell if
this continues on the other hand you
know within 20 years we'll have the
technology for doing genetic screening
of embryos and possibly in fixing
mutations and and so within 50 years
within two generations it probably won't
matter that much you know how the mating
market kind of plays out in terms of
which genes survive it's not like we're
in a kind of situation maybe a thousand
years ago where there's no way to kind
of fix the evolution through technology
that will happen I mean within a
generation or two pretty much everybody
is gonna be able to afford some kind of
genetic screening or manipulation you
know of embryos that that is quite
helpful but I think the short-term
problem is just people are frustrated
they can't find mates they can't have
good relationships women aren't getting
what they want men aren't getting what
they want
everybody is sad and frustrated
miserable
and I'm not you know that
and there's other countries that are
gonna face the same kinds of issues
maybe even worse like in China the
excess of males over females is gonna be
a huge issue and they are gonna have to
think very very carefully how do we
structure mating markets and families so
that we don't have a catastrophic level
of now they're just gonna ship like ten
billion guys over the Korean border with
knives and spoons to fight another war
they might do that they might they might
recall an AI certain areas of the world
who knows but yeah to get back to like
how did how its why I took us off on
that tangent there but how how can a guy
today and in his in his partner female
partner find the erotic energy that may
be deleted by this sort of a Galit Aryan
nature of our professional markets and
sort of the elimination of hyper hyper
gammy or hypergamy yeah in and one of
the first things I started writing about
was about BDSM and I found it very
appealing because you can intellectually
create a space that can tap into like
our primal urges and our instincts and I
wrote a lot about dominance in the
bedroom sort of sort dominance in your
day to day life and then and then
leading into the bedroom and then also
some explicit stuff about BDSM inside
the bedroom and I think I've found it
personally to be I'm gonna use this word
and laugh but like a safe space to
express some of those urges that we have
that are stifled by you know reasonable
societal norms okay like you know we're
not running around just bashing women
over the head and raping them whenever
we want right so but in a controlled
environment you can create sort of like
a fantasy environment that allows us to
get that real visceral feeling real
primal energy that if you haven't if you
haven't experienced it it's kind of hard
to describe so what what I know that BDS
I'm very fringy and it's very you know
people who look down on it because they
don't understand it I think and I find
it personally to be
a very high intellectual you know driven
experience where you need a big you know
high level of creativity and honesty and
openness and communication and it's
actually very sophisticated what role do
you see you know of fantasy space in in
sort of tapping into those feelings that
can sort of get us through this period
where you know yeah the mating markets
are gonna put people together that may
not have been put together in the past
something like that so I've given a
couple talks actually about the
evolutionary psychology of BDSM and I do
talk about kink and BDSM in my human
sexuality class I think it is
fascinating there's a lot of
misconceptions people have about it they
think it's all about whips and chains my
reading is you know the heart of BDSM is
basically power exchange roleplay and
how insane consensual and usually
consensual power exchange which is like
it's just like kids doing roleplay like
I'm gonna pretend to be the pirate
captain and you're gonna pretend to be
my captive and let's just see how that
plays out is that cool with you and if I
do anything you don't like just say the
safe word like red and we'll stop so the
power exchange means that a couple can
sort of rebalance the power that they
might have an ordinary life maybe the
guy can explore more assertiveness and
domination and and activity and kind of
be a little Bossier then he might feel
comfortable doing an ordinary life and
maybe the woman can be more submissive
and passive and overwhelmed and so forth
or vice versa you know whatever floats
your boat and it is a safe space where
you can explore your revolt psychology
or let's say the woman can explore her
hypergamy and she can say okay I know
you know you're only whatever a
journalist or a professor or a lawyer in
real life but imagine you were you know
a Mongol warlord or a Roman Emperor or
whatever let's let's game that out and
when people do that I've talked a lot of
people who are into kink they say you
discover so many new parts of yourself
you didn't know existed or you were kind
of vaguely aware of but you can let them
out you can let them play you can you
can turn them into an amazing expression
of creativity in fact and so I wish that
more couples therapists would kind of
even prescribe roleplay as a sort of
intervention that might help a lot of
relationships I've never met a girl that
didn't like having her hair pulled I
mean that's that's it's almost like a
universal statement that I can make and
my sample size is not insignificant and
related just there's none of the
squirrels around my house and just the
other day my five-year-old daughter was
like Daddy what is that squirrel doing
to the other squirrel and I looked out
there and they were mating but in the
process there was like a penetration and
then the male jumped up on the back of
the female and just just not on its neck
and just like in its neck and bit its
neck and bit its neck and then jump back
and did some more penetration and jump
back up on top and just bit its neck and
pinned it down and that kind of thing is
prevalent I think all across animal
species I mean I'm not a complete expert
yes if I mean 70 million years of mammal
evolution and four thousand species of
mammals and the males are typically you
know copulating so-called doggystyle
which often involves a bite on the feem
the back of the female's neck which is
kind of the equivalent of modern human
hair pulling all right it's deep deep
deep and it's across
and it's not some weird little thing
it's absolutely standard animal mating
behavior now what's interesting to me is
I find that I find a lot of resistance
to you know kink or BDSM from people who
would be considered like traditional
traditional right trad con kind of thing
and then you find you know the radical
lefties you know really into it or very
open-minded to it and you know what do
you what do you attribute that sort of
difference to when on the traditional
side you think that they may be more
aligned with our sort of animal
behaviors and leadership and dominance
and whatnot but then on the on the lefty
side where they want us to all be blank
slates and you know we're all the same
but yet there's a real openness to King
what do you what do you make about that
I think that's right if you if you go to
a BDSM conference almost everybody there
is far lefty gender feminist extremely
kind of sex positive but in a very
politically correct way and if you ask a
lot of conservatives about BDSM they
think it's it's weird and degenerate and
some like they have a sexual disgust
reaction to it it's on the one hand you
you could think well a traditional
marriage with sort of standard like
1950s gender roles already is a kind of
Power Exchange it's almost like a 24/7
right master yeah not slave but like
yeah Tom sub relationship toy so maybe
they don't kind of need to do the role
play cuz that's their whole life right
greenway great point should trad cons
are the epitome of 24/7 King yeah
quote I mean when I was growing up you
know in Ohio I saw a lot of my parents
friends and how their marriages worked
and it kind of what's that and at the
time or maybe later in college I thought
oh my god that's so patriarchal and
exploited of in a weird and but then
later the last few years I've thought
wait maybe maybe
a lot more consensual in a way than I
realized
like maybe the women were actually
choosing the guys who embodied that and
they wanted that and okay it's got pros
and cons but just like we shouldn't
judge people who go into a 24/7
master-slave relationship is like oh my
god that's terrible
maybe we shouldn't judge people who go
into a sort of trad life relationship
that is functionally equivalent in many
ways never thought of it like that
you know so I'm working on this book
proposal to do a next book that is
partly about kind of what can mainstream
relationships learn from these different
sexual subcultures right so let's say
you have a mainstream vanillin marriage
maybe you don't want to do full like
flogging and bondage but what can you
learn from BDSM that could help you
that's not too edgy but that's helpful
or what can like monogamous people learn
from polyamorous people and I think
there's a lot there's a lot of kind of
love hacks and relationship tools that
can be learned from these subcultures
including for kind of tribe life
conservatives and conversely I think you
know standard liberal professional
couples can learn a lot from like
Christian relationship advice and books
or from trad life books or red pill
books sounds like a fascinating book
that maybe everybody will read or nobody
will read yeah
but the danger is everybody is gonna
read it and go oh my god he's trying to
be like non-partisan about sexuality
yeah well so we're on the topic of
relationships and sort of family
formation if that's not a stretch from
where we just were nasty a few questions
and lead into sort of another topic here
but how where what role is the nuclear
family playing in the makeup of our
society today and how important is a
mitad monogamous relationship to sort of
our economic development our cultural
development the sustainability of our
society in general uh that's a big
question so I think on the one hand you
need a kind of mating and family system
that gives everybody a vested interests
or a reasonable shot at happiness that
having some kind of sexual relationship
and having kids somehow now there's a
lot to recommend traditional monogamous
marriage as a way to kind of give people
civilizational buy-in where they go yes
I really want to put down roots to have
a long term relationship to raise kids
cooperatively in a way that they're not
a burden on other people etc so it's
pretty good at solving a lot of problems
and that is why every major civilization
around the world that's lasted more than
a few hundred years and that as a big
population has normative marriage as the
main way that most people have
relationships and kids and of course the
elites are always more polygamists or
polyamorous and there's some people who
are left out but by and large if you
have one man young woman one woman then
you know the young men think well I
might have to fight for the tribe I
might have to work hard for a while but
I have a shot at like having at least
one woman and this is done through norms
norms mostly right so so this is this is
Peterson we're talking about and it's
not his idea right I think the fact that
people were giving him over saying
enforced monogamy like that he didn't
come up with that but this knows that
that's a standard term and it doesn't of
course it doesn't mean physically forced
it doesn't even need mean legally
enforced it can just mean honey don't
you want to find a young man to settle
down without parental enforced
and until you that you think that
directly leads to like increased
stability economic output
you know advancement of society etc
there's a lot of evidence from you know
evolutionary anthropologists like Johan
record Harvard and lots of other people
that you know all else being equal
monogamous marriage is a pretty good
system for reducing homicide rates and
violence and rape and warfare rates and
getting guys to be economically
productive instead of bitter slackers
right give them a reason I mean men men
are a beasts of burden but they won't
they won't serve if there's no real
reason to right and kids and a wife are
good good yeah it's a good motivator get
your ass up off the couch yeah so I mean
particularly monogamy plus capitalism is
a hugely powerful way to promote
economic growth because it means you
know both sexes have an interest in
maximizing the welfare of their family
and their prosperity no I think that
there would be there'll be some people
right now that would argue that we're
drifting away from this monogamous
committed committed model and not
necessarily moving towards willfully
purposely moving towards a explicit
non-monogamous structure but actually de
facto a de facto polygyny as it were and
this goes to the sort of the Chad and
the in cell conversation which is where
the whole Jordan Peterson neo comment
came from and I think what what I've
seen well through my personal experience
and through just talking to basically
thousands of guys over the last number
of years is that there's a the
distribution of sex partners is going is
concentrated in the hands of a smaller
smaller group of men leaving a larger
group of men without this incentive to
be economically productive and this
isn't happening because for any specific
or maybe it is policy reasons or whatnot
it's just sort of
an evolution that's happening right now
do you agree that that is the case and
do you have any can you attribute
anything to the cause of that I think
it's a huge problem that you have let's
say OkCupid dating apps they have really
good data where like the the upper 5 or
10% of the most attractive guys are
getting the vast majority female
interest and the lower 60% are basically
not competitive at all like they get no
interest from women browsers with women
it's pretty evenly distributed like guys
are a little more attracted to smart and
interesting creative and beautiful
younger women but most of the women have
a shot on the dating market at least of
getting a short-term boyfriend
so that's exaggerating the differences
between males the dating apps the fact
that you know if you're a really hot
rich young guy in Manhattan you can have
literally as many dates as you can
handle women professional women in
Manhattan have a much more serious
competitive situation where yes they can
find short term boyfriend but it's very
hard to get a guy quality guy to kind of
commit long term so I think the real
existential threat to the monogamous
marriage system is not it's not the
polyamorous people advocating open
relationships that are long-term bonds
rather the real threat is this kind of
extended casual sex life where people
are just doing kind of casual dating and
sequential kind of not too serious
relationships until their mid-30s right
and then they're kind of panicking like
oh my god clock's ticking right but
where did that come from I think that
came partly from the absurd extension of
educational credential ISM from like
only a tiny proportion of people saying
in school through the college degree to
everybody think I need a master's degree
it's the geographical mobility where
nobody's putting down roots until they
find a partner but they can't find a
partner to it put down roots and I think
it's also a common misunderstanding of
how you know the fertility curve looks
for women and men for men for that for
that matter right so I got into a very
interesting discussion with a guy on
Twitter a very conservative very
religious guy and we were talking about
this this very issue and he attributed a
decline in the marriage rate to
basically everything costing more right
and that we you know you have to have
more education you have to work harder
it takes more time to build your career
people are satisfied with their career
so they don't get married financial
security and I kept challenging him to
dig another layer deeper and he could
his brain just wouldn't get it and I
finally just tweeted it and I was like
the Federal Reserve was causing this
right like like basically inflation and
you know it's a very short-handed way of
saying it but like we've increased our
aggregate demand in our consumer markets
and housing markets education markets
and we increased our get demand by what
by putting women into the into the labor
force and so in some ways you can really
trace this desk dissatisfaction the
delayed marriage the decrease in
fertility rates you can trace it all the
way back through education and all the
way back to you know people you know
deciding to stop working in the home and
the abandonment of the traditional
family structure and so I'm wondering if
we're you know look is this what Trump
meant by make America great again I
don't know right but I think there's
people that look back to that time
period or look back and can just maybe
not even look back with it fondly but
even just look back and the kids can
give some attribution to the
the feminist movement that put women
into the workplace directly leading to
these circumstances environment that we
have now and look nobody I roll with and
myself is gonna say that like women
shouldn't have any you know women should
have all the opportunity in the world
that they won't make any decisions I'm
fine but there's consequences right and
so I think we're sort of seeing those
consequences today manifests himself in
these disrupted relationship markets and
dissatisfaction and then you get the
radical elements of this late wave
feminism just exacerbating all of it and
I guess what I'm wondering is like are
we going to find a way to it a is there
a rational reason to move back towards
an emphasis on earlier family formation
stricter enforcement of marriage laws
etcetera you know is there a real
positive outcome that we could say this
is we this is why we need to do this and
and what would we do and is anybody
actually gonna you know make any changes
I think there's a lot of factors that go
into people having this this deep kind
of economic pessimism and fear like I'm
not ready to start a family yet I can't
afford it
part of its housing policy right are
twin a friend on Twitter Noah Smith
tweets a lot about how absurdly
expensive it is in most major happening
cities to buy a house right and that's
not just because everybody wants to live
there it's because there are actual
government policies that are idiotic and
harmful right there's no policies in our
subsidies it's all that and still turn
down into our relationships yeah lose my
mind and nobody you know the politicians
and the economists don't typically think
about okay what exactly are the side
effects of minimizing new housing
construction in the Bay Area but it does
have effects of course I think secondly
you know as you point out the two income
couples absolutely everybody should have
the freedom to find a job but there are
side effects which is that the same
house that you know a man and
housewife would have been able to afford
fifty years ago now costs twice as much
because most couples are to two income
couples of course that and but people
didn't talk about that in the seventies
when there was this wave of women
entering the workforce that it will soon
become obligatory for most women right
they thought of it as a I want to say a
luxury but it was this is my choice this
is gonna be great it's gonna be great
for me it's gonna be great for everybody
yeah and then I think a third factor is
over parenting this sort of leftist idea
that oh if it's a blank slate
parenting's really hard because you have
the entire burden of shaping these
little people yourself as parents right
all the evolutionary psychologists and
behavior geneticists I know are very
relaxed parents because they're like we
have a baby it was born of many many
instincts shaped on millions of years
it's got genes I'm good you're good our
kids gonna be fine
to just roll with it just feed them and
they grow yeah and they'll be fine yeah
by contrast the planks laters are the
ones who do this this coddling and the
over parent the helicopter parenting the
tiger mothering all that stuff and they
over invest in their kids and drive
their kids nuts with all the
extracurriculars and it's catastrophic
because it means people delay having
kids until they think they can do all
that well I had of a theory that the
reason that the helicopter parenting I
think they now call bulldozer parenting
to like you have to clear every obstacle
out of the way for your child
why that's become more prevalent is
because the value of the egg is more
Vella it has higher value at the time of
conception and because there's a finite
supply of them it becomes even more
valuable so you're just there's so much
more anxiety around a successful outcome
whereas if you're banging him out from
18 to 24 and you've got eight and you
know sadly you have a miscarriage and
you know one of them is a screw-up and
you know just kind of there's there was
less of a mathematical emphasis on on
the eggs and now here we are you
this is my last chance and I have to do
absolutely everything I possibly can to
make sure that this child has every
opportunity then it's just I mean it's
really created a mutated market for
parenting and I see it you know with my
kids and I'm I'm one of those relaxed
parents but at the same time I'm also
like so I here's a little story my I had
a friend over with his kids and my 13
year old daughter wanted to climb the
tree in the backyard and she's like
daddy you know will he help me up and I
was like I'll help you up but I won't
help you down she's like okay so she you
know made the calculation and she's like
okay I helped her up and she was up
there for a while and then when it was
time for her to come down she got you
know real scared but she figured it out
by contrast my friends kids he's like
don't climb the tree you're gonna get
hurt you know and you know are we going
to teach your kid to try and fail or be
resilient or anti fragile whatever the
word is today if you're not giving them
out opportunity and you know to me it's
all tied together when you when you
break it down and say it's like
economics and it's policy it's feminist
policy it's labor force issues it you
know to me I'm trying to look at the big
picture and try to see how one we can
have these discussions about policy and
ideology and philosophy and see you know
what the hell comes our gonna be but you
know then I'm trying to turn it into a
practical application for for people
that I know and it's a I feel like I'm
running upstream you know with this I'm
gonna know another metaphor like a fish
a fish out of water it's like a whole
weird environment that it doesn't seem
to add up to me and you know I don't
think that that's getting any better of
course you can see this in exaggerated
form in Chinese parenting in the 90s and
the odds after they had the one-child
policy and if you're only allowed to
have one kid they invest like crazy in
it by contrast like my maternal
grandmother had 12 kids and I think you
know she and her husband took kind of as
more statistical approach like they knew
some of these kids will get into Harvard
MIT as they did and some of them will go
to a University of Cincinnati as they
did and some might not go to college and
and that's okay so
you can let the kids be who they are
instead of thinking well if I don't get
them into an elite school and they don't
have a thriving professional career then
then I'm failure like that's that's
terrible so the next thing that I wanted
to talk about was I was listening to
your podcast with Sam Harris and in it
you said that you had observed a
Cambrian explosion of mating options
what what did you mean by that and what
is the significance for us moving
forward and again try to explain a
couple of the things that you observed
so the Cambrian explosion is this
amazing thing that happened in an
evolution about five hundred thirty
million years ago where animals evolved
multicellular bodies and nervous systems
for the first time ever since life began
on earth four billion years ago and you
got this amazing diversification of
different body forms behaviors
biodiversity and and that Cambrian
explosion really led to you know the the
whole spectrum of modern animal life
from octopuses to mammals to birds etc
and I think analogously at the moment in
culture worldwide but especially in
American culture we're seeing a kind of
Cambrian explosion of different
relationship styles mating norms
different ways of people can interact
sexually short term long term whatever
and that spectrum includes everything
from trad life monogamous marriage to
so-called a relationship anarchy which
is a form of polyamory where you don't
really try to define your relationship
from a commitments to things like
monogamish relationships that are a
little bit open but not totally open to
you know polygynous cults to just
standard casual dating which is its own
kind of mating system in a way and it'll
be fascinating to see how this all
shakes out and which of those
relationship styles actually prove to be
viable in terms of people's happiness
well being and family structure and
having babies and all that and some of
them will crash and burn some of them
won't succeed and hopefully we'll keep
inventing new ones but I think America
has to kind of brace for the fact that
this is happening people are exploring
new options beyond monogamous marriage
and beyond just casual dating and it's a
big trend I mean more people are doing
these alternative relationships that our
gay and lesbian for example what kind of
percentage would you put on that well
people are often surprised to learn only
about 2% of people are gay or lesbian
and there's there's a lot of bisexual
women but homosexuality is a lot less
common than most folks think those folks
think it's about 10 percent it isn't
by contrast among Millennials and Gen Z
the proportion of them who are doing
some kind of consensual non-monogamy or
polyamory or open relationships is
somewhere between maybe 10 percent 25
percent you know because it's hard to
find good data on this but it's a least
that level know I wrote a book a while
back called sex at dawn you familiar
with this oh yeah yeah so I think the
basic premise was that pre-agricultural
homo sapiens were you know the mixed and
matched mates and they shared fruits and
berries and woolly mammoths and they
also shared their partners and that led
us you know from you know carried us
evolutionarily up until the agricultural
era do you think that the remnants of
that is still inside of us right now I
think there's a grain of truth in that
but my model of prehistory is sort of
halfway between the sexes Adhan model
which is quite polyamorous right and the
kind of traditional pair-bond
model that says well yeah our ancestors
kind of fooled around a bit when there
are teenagers and young adults but then
they tend to deform mostly a monogamous
pair bonds the lasted at least a few
years often a lifetime and that most
kids were born
into pair-bonded couples I think it is
true most kids were born into pair of
wanted couples the question is how
exclusive were the pair bonds my hunch
is that we're pretty flexible about that
that if the economic and social and
religious conditions favor strict
monogamy most people can do that most of
the time on the other hand if the social
economic religious conditions allow more
openness a lot of people quite like to
try that thank you very much yeah
and particularly if there's
contraception and good you know safer
sex barrier is STI testing yeah well you
know personally I've been in a long-term
relationship but you know I almost said
the word committed but you know it is
committed we are committed to each other
but it's also it's also open and we
definitely don't use the word poly
amorous we will use the word ethically
non-monogamous and so there's a
precondition for at all it's just
complete open honesty a ton of
communication and a respect for how the
other person is feeling about things and
what we have found and what I found
personally most so is that every time I
have a sort of mini relationship with a
third party or even just a single date
you know I've returned to my primary
relationship rejuvenated and excited and
sexually aroused even and I think that
there's some you know evolutionary
rationale for that I've heard of the
sperm competition and just a sense that
you need to like overwhelm other beyond
mates that may have been there but you
weren't there
I've at least found personally that some
people may argue that having an open
relationship would be the long-term
detrimental I found for myself that it's
long term positive and helpful and
healthy and has only strengthened the
relationship that I have with my
girlfriend and you know girlfriend I
feel like such an understated word for
the level of commitment and and and
partnership that we have but are you
hearing people sort of use that you know
that language and see it as a as a sort
of a sort of a support structure for a
long-term pair bond yeah I think it can
absolutely work that way I'm in a pretty
similar situation to you like a
long-term highly committed but open
relationship and it can work it requires
a lot of leveling up there's a steep
learning curve it can be very very
difficult at first particularly because
society doesn't offer a lot of support
and norms and role models for that but I
think that is the wave of the future
what confusion what confuses sort of
traditionalists and conservatives as
they think if it's not exclusive it
can't by definition be committed mm-hmm
or if you're polyed you can't possibly
have long-term relationships or if you
have an open relationship you can't
possibly provide stability and structure
for parenting and that's empirically
false a lot of people can do that but
your deeper point is can it actually
enrich and strengthen a relationship for
it not to be exclusive as long as
there's a pretty radical level of
honesty as long as you negotiate your
relationship agreements explicitly and
carefully and you you update them as you
need to and as long as you as long as
you choose outside partners also who
have the same abilities who have the
experience who can kind of know where
they fit into your life and you know
where you fit into their life
great you have to be honest with them -
yeah and you have to you have to be
upfront like on the first date you gotta
say I am in an open relationship is that
cool with you or you say it or the first
time you text them on even before the
first date yeah yeah well what's
interesting I want to tie this back to
sort of our earlier discussions of like
some game and sort of red pill stuff and
what I have always understood about game
which I think it's a bad rap it's people
talking about sort of pick up stuff but
really what it is is a signaling to your
partner that you have certain traits
that they should find attractive and I
think men that are just beginning their
sort of self-improvement journey
need to find ways to signal that they
have high levels of fitness to borrow
phrase when they may not be all the way
there just yet and I think that that's
okay and one of the things that came
comes up in talks in the sort of game
circles is that you know in order to
keep your your partner excited about you
one way to do it is for her to see that
other people still find you attractive
and so I think that some guys that will
call that like spinning plates or you
know other phrases but the idea is that
you know just flirt with somebody who's
in this in a supermarket and your wife
will see it and she'll be turned on and
it'll still got some some spark to it
and I guess that this the open
relationship for me does the same thing
and it's really curious because you go
out into the market the sex market and
you get another data point you know for
yourself and you get another data point
for your partner and for me it's always
just been such a wonderful confirmation
of how wonderful amazing my relationship
is and how much I love her and how hot
everything is and how we want to
continue doing that and so I think I've
seen sort of the civil ushion airy
component to you know the competitive
nature of the sexual marketplace as
being a benefit to preserving your
long-term spark which in turn will then
give you a more stable long-term
relationship which would be better for
your kids better for the economy better
for all this thing and so I guess this
is a long way of me saying the game and
sort of even the tease of an open
relationship
it's good to be good for good for the
country in the long term and maybe
another one of these components that
we're talking about like how are we
going to manage our relationships and
ourselves as men in this environment
that is attacking masculinity attacking
the expressions of manhood and power and
dominance and all the things that we've
been talking about that have bubbled up
all the way into our national politics
and all through all the various elements
of our cultures and institutions and our
universities and our media and the
entertainment and every which possible
way that you can take a look at the
human experience you know this this
dialogue is going on this tension this
drama people call it a war you know and
we're all dragged into it we're all part
of it today and the question for me and
for my readers and my listeners is like
how are we as individuals gonna do the
best that we can for ourselves and in
turn for our family our community and
then for our nation and I think that in
this conversation we've covered a ton of
those things and I think we've really
put everything into the context and I
really appreciate it and I appreciate
your time and I appreciate your
expertise and your graciousness and
having me in your home and I just want
to say thank you it's been a real
pleasure to talk to you very welcome and
I hope that we have a chance to do it
again yeah me too it's been a great
interview and I'm glad we were able to
connect so many dots together yeah
thanks a lot I appreciate it thank you
all right